Guide to the Early Rice Institute records, 1844-1941 UA 101
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
- Series III: Rice Institute, 1882-1941 (bulk 1891-1918) (Boxes 88-97, 116), 241489
  - Subseries E: Chronological files, 241500
    - 1897, 241514 (Box 95, Folder 7)
    - 1898, 241513 (Box 95, Folder 8)
    - 1899, 241512 (Box 95, Folder 9)
    - 1900, 241511 (Box 95, Folder 10)
    - 1901, 241510 (Box 95, Folder 11)
    - 1902, 241509 (Box 95, Folder 12)
    - 1903, 241508 (Box 95, Folder 13)
    - 1904, 241507 (Box 95, Folder 14)
    - 1905, 241506 (Box 95, Folder 15)
    - 1906, 241505 (Box 95, Folder 16)
    - 1907, 241504 (Box 95, Folder 17)
    - 1908, 241503 (Box 95, Folder 18)
    - 1909, 241502 (Box 95, Folder 19)
    - Undated, 241501 (Box 95, Folder 20)
  - Subseries F: Board inquiries to other universities and colleges, 241495
    - Statements regarding intentions for Rice Institute, 1900, 241499 (Box 96, Folder 1)
    - Research on charitable institutions, 241498 (Box 96, Folder 2)
    - Inquiry correspondence, 241497 (Box 97, Folder 1)
    - Charters and reports from other institutions, 241496 (Box 97, Folder -)
  - Subseries G: Camp Sterett records, 1917-1933, 241490
    - Charter, by-laws, correspondence, financial records, 1917-1927, 241494 (Box 116, Folder 1)
    - Charter, by-laws, correspondence, financial records, 1928-1930, 241493 (Box 116, Folder 2)
    - Charter, by-laws, correspondence, financial records, 1930-33, 241492 (Box 116, Folder 3)
    - Corporate seal, 241491 (Box 116, Folder 4)
- Series IV: WMR business records & land titles, 1844-1936, bulk 1880-1900 (Boxes 98-113, 117), 241263
  Financial and legal correspondence, receipts, promissory notes, and records of land holdings (titles and deeds) in this series document Wm. M. Rice's business dealings and name many of his financial holdings, business agents and legal advisors.
  - Subseries A: Business correspondence & documents, 1858-1900, 241461
    - Adams, Charles T., 1896-1899, 241488 (Box 98, Folder 1)
    - Baker, Botts, Baker & Lovett, 1894-1900, 241487 (Box 98, Folder 2-4)
    - Capitol Hotel financial records, 1884-1899, 241486 (Box 98, Folder 5)
    - Cohn, A.B., 1896-1897, 241485 (Box 98, Folder 6-7)
    - Cohn, A.B., 1898-1899, undated, 241484 (Box 99, Folder 1-3)
    - Doucette, A.B., 1897-1899, 241483 (Box 99, Folder 4)
    - First National Bank of Houston, incl. Deposit & withdrawal slips, 1890- 1900, 241482 (Box 99, Folder 5-8)
    - First National Bank, Orange, TX, 1897-1900, 241481 (Box 100, Folder 1)
    - Galveston Wharf Company, 1893, 1898-1899, 241480 (Box 100, Folder 2)
    - Gold Eagle Lodge shares, 1880, 241479 (Box 100, Folder 3)
    - Granberry, P.M., 1897-1900, 241478 (Box 100, Folder 4)
    - Hervey, Frank A., 1897-1899, 241477 (Box 100, Folder 5)
    - Houston Brazos and Northern Railway Company, 1899-1900, 241476 (Box 100, Folder 6)
    - Houston Brick Works Company, 1884-1908, 241475 (Box 100, Folder 7)
    - Houston Drug Company, 1899-1900, 241474 (Box 100, Folder 8)
    - Houston Land and Trust Company, 1897-1900, 241473 (Box 100, Folder 9)
    - Mackey block (concerning), 1896-1900, 241472 (Box 101, Folder 1-2)
    - Merchants and Planters Oil Company, 1893-1900, 241471 (Box 101, Folder 3)
    - Moody, W.L. & Co., 1894-1899, 241470 (Box 101, Folder 4)
    - O'Brien, J.P., 1892-1901, 241469 (Box 101, Folder 5)
    - Parks, A.R. & J.W., 1858-1869, 241468 (Box 101, Folder 6)
    - Rice, Frederick A., 1882-1900, 241467 (Box 101, Folder 7-8)
    - Rice, William Marsh, Jr., 1897-1899, 241466 (Box 101, Folder 9)
    - Rice, William Marsh, 1900, 241465 (Box 102, Folder 1)
    - Rucker, W.G., 1895-1900, 241464 (Box 102, Folder 2)
    - Sabine Tram Company, 1896-1900, 241463 (Box 102, Folder 3)
    - S.M. Swenson and Sons, 1891-1900, 241462 (Box 102, Folder 4)
  - Subseries B: Chronological correspondence and documents, 241450
    - 1858-1862, 241460 (Box 102, Folder 4a)
    - 1880, 1882, 1884, 1892, 241459 (Box 102, Folder 5)
    - 1893, 1894, 241458 (Box 102, Folder 6)
    - 1895, 241457 (Box 103, Folder 1)
    - 1896-1897, 241456 (Box 103, Folder 2)
    - 1898, 241455 (Box 103, Folder 3)
    - 1899, 241454 (Box 103, Folder 4)
    - 1900, 241453 (Box 103, Folder 5)
    - WMR correspondence only, 1900, 241452 (Box 103, Folder 6)
    - Undated instruments and correspondence, 241451 (Box 103, Folder 7)
  - Subseries C: Receipts and business documents, 241316
    - Abilene Ice Company, 1897, 241449 (Box 104, Folder 1)
    - Abel, J.A., n.d., 241448 (Box 104, Folder 2)
    - Abney, W.B., 1897-1899, 241447 (Box 104, Folder 3)
    - Alamo Iron Works, 1897, 241446 (Box 104, Folder 4)
    - American Manufacturing Co., 1899, 241445 (Box 104, Folder 5)
    - Ater, A.B., 1897-1898, 241444 (Box 104, Folder 6)
    - Barbour, Edmund D., 1898, 241443 (Box 104, Folder 7)
    - Bartine, J.D., 1899, 241442 (Box 104, Folder 8)
    - Beissner, F.W., 1898, 241441 (Box 104, Folder 9)
    - Benson, C.P., 1896-1898, 241440 (Box 104, Folder 10)
    - Best and Russell Co., 1897, 241439 (Box 104, Folder 11)
    - Bocock, C.W., 1897, 241438 (Box 104, Folder 12)
    - Brewster, Mary C., 1878-1899, 241437 (Box 104, Folder 13)
    - Brooke, H.D., 1898-1899, 241436 (Box 104, Folder 14)
    - Burkitt, G.W., 1897, 241435 (Box 104, Folder 15)
    - Calcasieu River Lumber Co., 1898, 241434 (Box 104, Folder 16)
    - Campbell, W. S., 1899-1900, 241433 (Box 104, Folder 17)
    - Carpenter, Charles, 1896-1899, 241432 (Box 104, Folder 18)
    - Carson, Philip, 1897-1899, 241431 (Box 104, Folder 19)
    - Central Iron Works, 1897, 241430 (Box 104, Folder 20)
    - Chew, J.C., 1899, 241429 (Box 104, Folder 21)
    - Citizens Electric Light and Power Co., 1900, 241428 (Box 104, Folder 22)
    - C.L. Jones & Sons, 1897, 241427 (Box 104, Folder 23)
    - Cregan, B.T., 1896-1899, 241426 (Box 104, Folder 24)
    - Darragh, John, 1898, 241425 (Box 104, Folder 25)
    - De Cordova & Sons, 1894-1900, 241424 (Box 104, Folder 26)
    - Dobbs, J.L., 1897, 241423 (Box 104, Folder 27)
    - Elms, Chas. S., 1898, 241422 (Box 104, Folder 28)
    - Ennis, Cornelius, 1870-1896, 241421 (Box 104, Folder 29)
    - Eaton, Alfred P., 1897, 241420 (Box 104, Folder 30)
    - Ferrell, C.C., 1898, 241419 (Box 104, Folder 31)
    - Fifth Avenue Trust Co., 1899, 241418 (Box 104, Folder 32)
    - First National Bank, Lake Charles, 1898-1899, 241417 (Box 104, Folder 33)
    - First Presbyterian Church, Houston, 1895, 241416 (Box 104, Folder 34)
    - Foster, W.H., 1895, 241415 (Box 104, Folder 35)
    - Franklin, Robert M., 1898, 241414 (Box 104, Folder 36)
    - Franklin, Thomas R., 1897-1898, 241413 (Box 104, Folder 37)
    - Freuss, Grace, 1897, 241412 (Box 104, Folder 38)
    - George, Mary C., 1898, 241411 (Box 104, Folder 39)
    - Gibbons Manufacturing Co., 1898, 241410 (Box 104, Folder 40)
    - Gibbs, W.S., 1899, 241409 (Box 104, Folder 41)
    - Graham, G.A., 1894, 241408 (Box 104, Folder 42)
    - Graham, M.K., 1899, 241407 (Box 104, Folder 43)
    - Gregory, J.B., 1899, 241406 (Box 104, Folder 44)
    - Groesbeeck, Abraham, 1899, 241405 (Box 104, Folder 45)
    - Goresbeeck & Rice, 1857-1859, 241404 (Box 104, Folder 46)
    - Hamilton, H., 1898, 241403 (Box 104, Folder 47)
    - Hamilton Bros., 1898, 241402 (Box 104, Folder 48)
    - H.M. Trueheart & Co., 1889, 241401 (Box 104, Folder 49)
    - House, Thomas William, 1898, 241400 (Box 104, Folder 50)
    - Houston & Galveston Navigation Co., 1866, 241399 (Box 104, Folder 51)
    - Houston & Great Northern, 1871, 241398 (Box 104, Folder 52)
    - Houston Drug Co., 1899-1900, 241397 (Box 104, Folder 53)
    - Houston, East and West Texas Railway Co., 1897, 241396 (Box 104, Folder 54)
    - Houston Electric Light and Power Co., 1890, 241395 (Box 104, Folder 55)
    - Houston Gas Light Co., 1898, 241394 (Box 104, Folder 56)
    - Houston & Texas Central Railway Co., 1861-1870, 241393 (Box 104, Folder 57)
    - Houston Ice & Brewing Co., 1892-1898, 241392 (Box 104, Folder 58)
    - Houston Insurance Co., 1867-1869, 241391 (Box 104, Folder 59)
    - Houston Lyceum, 1899, 241390 (Box 104, Folder 60)
    - Houston Post, 1899, 241389 (Box 104, Folder 61)
    - Hunter, William, 1899, 241388 (Box 104, Folder 62)
    - Hyatt, F.A., 1896-1899, 241387 (Box 104, Folder 63)
    - Jackson, Hugh, 1898, 241386 (Box 104, Folder 64)
    - Jefferson Ice Co., 1897, 241385 (Box 104, Folder 65)
    - Jefferson Real Estate and Abstract Co., 1899, 241384 (Box 104, Folder 66)
    - Jemison, E.S., 1893-1894, 241383 (Box 104, Folder 67)
    - Jenkins, J.H., 1896-1898, 241382 (Box 104, Folder 68)
    - Johnson & Akin, 1899, 241381 (Box 104, Folder 69)
    - Kirby, R.H., 1899, 241380 (Box 104, Folder 70)
    - Kley (?), Ida B., 1900, 241379 (Box 104, Folder 71)
    - Korst, G.E., 1899, 241378 (Box 104, Folder 72)
    - Lawlor, Jas., 1897-1898, 241377 (Box 104, Folder 73)
    - LeDuc, Marie, n.d., 241376 (Box 104, Folder 74)
    - Liberty National Bank, 1899, 241375 (Box 104, Folder 75)
    - McFarland, A., 1897, 241374 (Box 104, Folder 76)
    - McPhaill, R.C., 1899, 241373 (Box 104, Folder 77)
    - Mahan, Jno. J., 1895-1897, 241372 (Box 104, Folder 78)
    - Marks, H.R., 1867-1899, 241371 (Box 104, Folder 79)
    - Martin & George, 1896-1897, 241370 (Box 104, Folder 80)
    - Matthews & Browning, 1898, 241369 (Box 104, Folder 81)
    - Mayer, Kahn & Freiberg, 1897, 241368 (Box 104, Folder 82)
    - Miller, L., 1895, 241367 (Box 104, Folder 83)
    - Mills, Chas. Edgar, 1897, 241366 (Box 104, Folder 84)
    - Mills, J.E., 1897, 241365 (Box 104, Folder 85)
    - New York and Texas Land Co., 1898-1899, 241364 (Box 105, Folder 1)
    - Nichols, F. McC., 1897, 241363 (Box 105, Folder 2)
    - O'Neal, W.H., n.d., 241362 (Box 105, Folder 3)
    - Parker, Charles E., 1896, 241361 (Box 105, Folder 4)
    - Parker, Edwin B., 1899, 241360 (Box 105, Folder 5)
    - Porter, George L., 1886-1899, 241359 (Box 105, Folder 6)
    - Porter, Hugh, 1897, 241358 (Box 105, Folder 7)
    - Pruitt, Ed., 1896, 241357 (Box 105, Folder 8)
    - Randolph, A.T., 1896-1900, 241356 (Box 105, Folder 9)
    - Raphael, Emmanuel, 1897-1898, 241355 (Box 105, Folder 10)
    - Rees & Rees, 1897, 241354 (Box 105, Folder 11)
    - Rice & Nichols, 1857-1860, 241353 (Box 105, Folder 12)
    - Robinson, Mary L., 1897, 241352 (Box 105, Folder 13)
    - Ryan, Rosine, 1899, 241351 (Box 105, Folder 14)
    - San Antonio & Brownsville Railway Co., 1899, 241350 (Box 105, Folder 15)
    - Scott, C.T., 1899, 241349 (Box 105, Folder 16)
    - Scott, T.M., 1897-1899, 241348 (Box 105, Folder 17)
    - Shepard, D.P., 1897, 241347 (Box 105, Folder 18)
    - Simmler, J.H., 1897, 241346 (Box 105, Folder 19)
    - Sligh, W. B., 1896, 241345 (Box 105, Folder 20)
    - Smith, Chas. Oliver, 1896, 241344 (Box 105, Folder 21)
    - Stanberry, A.B., 1897, 241343 (Box 105, Folder 22)
    - Steiner, Jno., 1896-1898, 241342 (Box 105, Folder 23)
    - Stephens, R.B., 1896-1899, 241341 (Box 105, Folder 24)
    - Sydnor, Ella Hutchins, 1898, 241340 (Box 105, Folder 25)
    - Terry, Judge J.W., 1897, 241339 (Box 105, Folder 26)
    - Texas Life Insurance Co., 1897, 241338 (Box 105, Folder 27)
    - Texas Loan & Investment Co., 1897, 241337 (Box 105, Folder 28)
    - Texas Star Soap Co. of 1891, 1892, 241336 (Box 105, Folder 29)
    - Texas State Historical Association, 1898, 241335 (Box 105, Folder 30)
    - Thomson & Donnan, 1892-1900, 241334 (Box 105, Folder 31)
    - Tinsley, Thomas, 1899, 241333 (Box 105, Folder 32)
    - Tomlinson, John C., 1896-1898, 241332 (Box 105, Folder 33)
    - Turner, William Baker, 1898, 241331 (Box 105, Folder 34)
    - Tyler Ice Co., 1897, 241330 (Box 105, Folder 35)
    - United States Express Co., 1897, 241329 (Box 105, Folder 36)
    - Wallis, C.L., 1896-1897, 241328 (Box 105, Folder 37)
    - W.B. Wallis & Co., 1896-1897, 241327 (Box 105, Folder 38)
    - Wetherbee, W.O., 1893-1898, 241326 (Box 105, Folder 39)
    - Whitaker, A., 1892-1897, 241325 (Box 105, Folder 40)
    - Whittelseay, J.E., 1898, 241324 (Box 105, Folder 41)
    - Wm. D. Cleveland & Co., 1897-1899, 241323 (Box 105, Folder 42)
    - Wm. M. Rice & Co., 1853-1866, 241322 (Box 105, Folder 43)
    - William M. Rice Building, 1894, 241321 (Box 105, Folder 44)
    - Wilson, Harvey T.D., 1899, 241320 (Box 105, Folder 45)
    - Wingate, Thomas C., 18999, 241319 (Box 105, Folder 46)
    - South Texas National Bank, credit and return slips, 241318 (Box 106, Folder 1-8)
    - South Texas National Bank, correspondence, 1895-1900, 241317 (Box 106, Folder 9-10)
  - Subseries D: Financial and legal documents, 241305
    - 1854, 1860, 1863, 241315 (Box 107, Folder 1)
    - 1865-1866, 241314 (Box 107, Folder 2)
    - 1867-1869, 241313 (Box 107, Folder 3)
    - 1870-1873, 1879, 1881, 1888, 241312 (Box 107, Folder 4)
    - 1891-1900, 241311 (Box 107, Folder 5)
    - 1882 WMR Will, 241310 (Box 107, Folder 6)
    - Property inventory, 241309 (Box 107, Folder 7)
    - Checks, deposit slips (Swenson and Sons Bank, NY), 241308 (Box 107, Folder 8)
    - Bills and receipts, 1895-1899, 241307 (Box 108, Folder 1)
    - Rice Ranch, 1892-1900, 241306 (Box 108, Folder 2)
  - Subseries E: Original land titles and related documents, 241264
    - General by year, 241299
      - 1844-1855, 241304 (Box 109, Folder 1)
      - 1857, 241303 (Box 109, Folder 2)
      - 1858-1876, incl. one Austin College bond, 241302 (Box 109, Folder 3)
      - 1880s-1890s, 241301 (Box 109, Folder 4)
      - Undated, 241300 (Box 109, Folder 5)
    - General by County name (Texas Counties unless otherwise noted), 241292
      - Cameron and Sabine Counties, Louisiana; Hampden Co., Mass.; Somerset Co., New Jersey, 1883-1898, 241298 (Box 110, Folder 1)
      - Austin, Bastrop, Bexar, Bosque, Burnet, 1868-1905, 241297 (Box 110, Folder 2)
      - Collin, Comanche, Denton, Falls, Fayette, Fort Bend, Galveston, Gonzales, Grayson, 1868-1898, 241296 (Box 110, Folder 3)
      - Harris, 1866-1904, 241295 (Box 110, Folder 4-5)
      - Trinity, Tyler, 1880-1903, 241294 (Box 110, Folder 6)
      - Uvalde, Walker, Wharton, Young, 1870-1907, 241293 (Box 110, Folder 7)
    - Townsite Syndicate Land Title documents, 241270
      - Bastrop County, 1868-1913, 241291 (Box 111, Folder 1)
      - Bexar, Bosque, Brazos Counties, 1867-1892, 241290 (Box 111, Folder 2)
      - Caldwell, Collin, Colorado, Comanche Counties, 1851-1890, 241289 (Box 111, Folder 3)
      - Dallas County, 1845-1902, 241288 (Box 111, Folder 4)
      - Denton County, 1855-1898, 241287 (Box 111, Folder 5)
      - Ellis County, 1870-1908, 241286 (Box 111, Folder 6)
      - Erath County, 1847-1894, 241285 (Box 111, Folder 7)
      - Falls, Fayette, Fort Bend Counties, 1851-1901, 241284 (Box 111, Folder 8)
      - Freestone, Galveston, Grayson Counties, 1871-1907, 241283 (Box 112, Folder 1)
      - Hill, Hunt, Jasper Counties, 1856-1900, 241282 (Box 112, Folder 2)
      - Jefferson, Johnson, Kaufman Counties, 1855-1904, 241281 (Box 112, Folder 3)
      - Lampasas, Lee Counties, 1894-1936, 241280 (Box 112, Folder 4)
      - Limestone County, 1866-1921, 241279 (Box 112, Folder 5)
      - Madison, Marion, Mason, McClennan, McCulloch, 1855-1898, 241278 (Box 112, Folder 6)
      - Menard & Milam Counties, 1845-1891, 241277 (Box 113, Folder 1)
      - Montague, Montgomery Counties, 1879-1897, 241276 (Box 113, Folder 2)
      - Navarro County, 1858-1903, 241275 (Box 113, Folder 3)
      - Newton, Parker, Polk, Refugio Counties, 1863-1886, 241274 (Box 113, Folder 4)
      - Robertson County, 1866-1921, 241273 (Box 113, Folder 5)
      - San Saba, Tarrant, Tom Green Counties, 1878-1898, 241272 (Box 113, Folder 6)
      - Travis, Washington Counties, 1856-1878, 241271 (Box 113, Folder 7)
    - Townsite Syndicate Chronological Files, 1869-1904, 241265
      - 1869-1900, Trustees, 241269 (Box 117, Folder 1)
      - 1897-1899, C.E. Davis, 241268 (Box 117, Folder 2)
      - 1869-1894, 241267 (Box 117, Folder 3)
      - 1895-1904, 241266 (Box 117, Folder 4)
- Series V: William Marsh Rice, personal and family correspondence, 1867-1900 (Box 114), 241246
  This series includes a small amount of family correspondence, personal receipts for items such as clothing at Lord &Taylor, and Wm. M. Rice's certificate of membership in the Holland Lodge No. 1 of the Ancient, Free and Accepted Masons.
  - Baldwin, Adele M., 1896, 241262 (Box 114, Folder 1)
  - Blinn, Frederick L., 1899, 241261 (Box 114, Folder 2)
  - Brown, Anne Baldwin, 1896, 241260 (Box 114, Folder 3)
  - Deane, Maria, 1898 (cousin), 241259 (Box 114, Folder 4)
  - McKee, Carrie A., 1896 (niece), 241258 (Box 114, Folder 5)
  - McKee, Charlotte S., 1898-1899 (sister), 241257 (Box 114, Folder 6)
  - Olds, Minvera Rice, 1899 (sister), 241256 (Box 114, Folder 7)
  - Rice, Charlotte Maria Baldwin, 1898-1900 (sister-in-law), 241255 (Box 114, Folder 8)
  - Rice, Frederick Allyn, 1867-1889 (brother), 241254 (Box 114, Folder 9)
  - Rice, George Converse, 1899 (nephew), 241253 (Box 114, Folder 10)
  - Rice, Horace Baldwin, 1892-1896 (nephew), 241252 (Box 114, Folder 11)
  - Rice, Minnie, 1898-1899 (niece), 241251 (Box 114, Folder 12)
  - Turnure, Mary E., n.d. (relation?), 241250 (Box 114, Folder 13)
  - Personal invoices (Lord & Taylor, etc.), 241249 (Box 114, Folder 14)
  - William Marsh Rice, Mason membership certificate, 1880, 241248 (Box 114, Folder 15)
  - William Marsh Rice to Frederick Allyn, from Mexico (scans provided by Houston Metropolitan Research Center), ca. 1964; 241247 (Box 114, Folder 16)
- Series VI: Correspondence between W. M. Rice, A. B. Cohn, and business partners, 1900 (Box 117)
  - Correspondence between W. M. Rice, A. B. Cohn, and business partners, 1900 (Box 117, Folder 5)